UH Veteran's Office Records, 1944-1958
University of Houston Libraries
UH Veteran's Office Records
1944-1958
University of Houston. Veteran's Office.
This collection contains material pertaining to the university and government-sponsored office for the support and advising of veteran students during the 1940s and 1950s. The office provided assistance in application for admission to the university and obtaining compensation through the GI Bill. A special housing bureau helped veterans and their families locate places to live. Materials include budgets, correspondence, and UH Veteran's registration packets dating from 1944-1958.
2 Boxes; 1 Linear Foot
1977-006
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Organization History
The University of Houston played an important part in the United States' efforts during the Second World War. Among its many contributions, the institution housed the first Naval School established in a college, training more than five thousand Navy personnel and several hundred Army and Navy pilots. Following the war, many of the nation's servicemen and women returned to colleges and universities to take advantage of the Servicemen's Readjustment Act of 1944 - better known as the GI Bill of Rights. Under the GI Bill, veterans received up to $500 a year from the government to cover tuition and fees as well as a monthly stipend.
Just as the University of Houston contributed to the war effort, following the war it contributed to the education of thousands of returning veterans. Dr. W.W. Kemmerer, assistant to the university president, strongly influenced the university's successful shift from a wartime to a peacetime stance. The postwar years were an era of significant growth for the fledgling institution. Many UH students used the GI Bill to further training obtained in the military, learn a vocational trade, or pursue college degrees. Enrollment for Fall semester 1944 reached 2,720, a significant increase from the 1,104 students just a year before. By the 1947-1948 school year enrollment reached 10,882.
To aid veterans in their transition from military to student life, UH established a guidance program with Richard O. Jonas as chief counselor and Roy A. Crouch as head of the office of psychological services. In December 1944 the U.S. Veterans Administration selected the University of Houston as the site for an official VA Advisement Center, augmenting the guidance program's effectiveness. The office provided assistance in application for admission to the university and obtaining compensation through the GI Bill. A special housing bureau helped veterans and their families locate places to live. Counselors, often former members of the armed forces themselves, aided ex-soldiers with registration, career guidance, and overall readjustment to civilian life.
Scope and Contents
The UH Veteran's Office Records contain material pertaining to the university and government-sponsored office for the support and advising of veteran students during the 1940s and 1950s. Dates for items in the collection range from 1944 to 1958, with the bulk of the material dating from the late 1940s.
The collection is arranged into nine series: Veteran's Office, Veteran's Staff Meetings, Budget, Correspondence with Veteran's Administration, Veteran's Administration Field Manual for Training Officers, Guidance Office, Veteran's Service Center, Forms, and Miscellaneous. The original arrangement has been kept intact where possible, however some minor rearrangement was necessary to facilitate research. Material is grouped chronologically within each series. Folder headings used by the originators have been adhered to where possible. For additional information on Veteran's affairs at the University of Houston, researchers should also consult the Veteran's Village Records.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Related Material
Veteran's Village Records, Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries.
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Index Terms
Terms are either Library of Congress Subject Headings or taken from local sources.
Subjects
Veterans Education
Subjects (Organizations)
University of Houston; University of Houston. Veteran's Office.; University of Houston History.
Formats
Correspondence; Budgets; Minutes
Detailed Description
- Veteran's Office (Box 1, Folder 1-21)
  There are twenty-one folders in this series containing items dating from 1944 to 1951. Material in this series consists of general correspondence between Veteran's Office personnel and University of Houston administrators, as well as some Veteran's Administration and other assorted letters.
  - Veteran's Office, June-December 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Veteran's Office, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Veteran's Office, January-May 1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Veteran's Office, June-December 1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Veteran's Office, February-June 1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Veteran's Office, July-September 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Veteran's Office, October-December 1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Veteran's Office, January-June 1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Veteran's Office, July-October 1947 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Veteran's Office, November 1947 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Veteran's Office, December 1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Veteran's Office, January 1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Veteran's Office, February-August 1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Veteran's Office, September-December 1948 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Veteran's Office, January-June 1949 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Veteran's Office, July-December 1949 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Veteran's Office, February-June 1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Veteran's Office, July-December 1950 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Veteran's Office, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Veteran's Office, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Veteran's Office, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Veteran's Staff Meetings (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  The three folders in this series contain minutes and notes from meetings held from 1946 to 1947.
  - Veteran's Staff Meetings, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Veteran's Staff Meetings, January-May 1947 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Veteran's Staff Meetings, June-December 1947 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Budget (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
  There are three folders in this series. Material dating from 1948 to August 1949 is largely in the form of ledger sheets and financial summaries.
  - Budget, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Budget, January-March 1949 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Budget, April-August 1949 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence with Veteran's Administration (Box 2, Folder 7-14)
  There are eight folders in this series with material dating from 1947 through 1949. Items focus exclusively on correspondence with the Veteran's Administration. [Note: this material was separated from other general correspondence (i.e., what is now the Veteran's Office series) in the collection's original arrangement.]
  - Correspondence with Veteran's Administration, [January] 1947 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with Veteran's Administration, May-June 1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with Veteran's Administration, July-August 1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence with Veteran's Administration, September-December 1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence with Veteran's Administration, January-March 1949 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence with Veteran's Administration, April-June 1949 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence with Veteran's Administration, July-September 1949 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence with Veteran's Administration, October-December 1949 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Veteran's Administration Field Manual for Training Officers (Box 2, Folder 15)
  The one folder in this series is a guide published in May 1946 by the Vocational Rehabilitation and Education Division of the Houston, Texas Regional VA office. It compiles Veteran's Administration regulations and procedures for personnel working with veterans in higher education. Organizational charts and specific instructions for completing various forms are included.
  - VA Field Manual for Training Officers, May 1946 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Guidance Office (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
  There are three folders in this series with items dating from 1947 to 1950. Material in this series includes floor plans, a blueprint, and correspondence with university administration concerning the construction of an office space to house the UH Veteran's Office. It also contains specific registration procedures.
  - Floor Plans and Correspondence, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Procedures and Regulations, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Blueprint, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Veteran's Service Center (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
  The two folders in this series contain material from August 1945 through 1948, and some undated items. It focuses on information dealing with a Veteran's service center located off campus, for ex-military personnel in the greater Houston area.
  - Veteran's Service Center, August 1945-May 1947 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Veteran's Service Center, December 1947-1948 and undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Forms (Box 2, Folder 21-25)
  There are five folders in this series containing various forms and registration material required of veterans by the Veteran's Administration and the University of Houston. Material dates from 1945 to 1950.
  - U.S. Veteran's Administration, April 1945-June 1950 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - UH Veteran's Registration, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - UH Veteran's Registration, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - UH Veteran's Registration, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - UH Veteran's Registration Package, [1950] (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  The two folders in this series contain material from July 1946 and 1958. Documents include vocational school class lists and a copy of The Wesleyan, a Methodist students' group newsletter.
  - Vocational School Class Lists, July 1946 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - The Wesleyan, January 1958 (Box 2, Folder 27)